Most AI agent memory systems fail in one of two ways.
They either forget useful prior work, or preserve too much raw context and call it memory.
Tree Ring Memory starts from a different premise: memory should age.
Fresh work stays detailed. Older learning compresses into rings. Failures become scars. Durable truths become heartwood. Future ideas stay as seeds.
This is not a hosted memory service or a vector database wrapper. It is a framework-agnostic memory lifecycle layer for AI agents.
The current public runtime is Rust-native: CLI, SQLite and FTS storage, explainable recall, import and export, audit, consolidation, maintenance, adapters, and TUI.
Install the CLI, initialize a local memory root, store one concise project lesson, recall it by query, and record evaluated outcomes with source references.
Evaluated outcomes matter because memory should not treat every claim as durable truth.
A promoted evaluation can become heartwood. A rejected experiment can become a scar, so future agents do not repeat the same failed path.
The privacy boundary matters too. Tree Ring Memory does not scrape transcripts, run a hidden recorder, or turn terminal pulses into durable memory.
Durable writes are explicit: remember, evidence, import, consolidation, maintenance, TUI action, or deliberate agent action.
Tree Ring Memory is in protocol-preview status. What should a portable, local-first memory layer get right before deeper framework bridges land?
Try it, break it, and leave feedback in the launch issue.